Okay, next section, the esophagus.
The very first disorder that we want to talk about
is a TE fistula, a tracheoesophageal fistula.
Let's remind ourselves that a fistula
is an abnormal connection between two tubes,
and in this particular case,
the abnormal connection is going to be
between the trachea and the esophagus,
and of course, this is a congenital defect.
Now, there are multiple different variants,
however, we're just going to focus on the most common variant
and go through a couple principles.
So in the most common variant,
what we have is we have a proximal esophagus
that is atretic.
Atretic means that it ends in a blind pouch
or a blind loop,
so we have proximal esophageal atresia,
and then when you look at the distal esophagus,
it comes off the trachea,
so up here would be the trachea,
and then you've got the distal esophagus
coming off the trachea,
and that's where the fistula is.
There's a connection between the distal esophagus
and the trachea.
Now, in this particular case,
the clinical findings are all based on this anatomy,
so once you understand the anatomy,
everything is downhill.
You can imagine that when the baby consumes food,
it's going to go into this blind pouch,
and then it's going to shoot back up,
so the patient or the baby is going to have vomiting.
Another important feature of having this atresia
of the esophagus is that,
remember that the baby folds around in amniotic fluid,
and the amount of amniotic fluid
is basically a function of two things.
The baby produces amniotic fluid from the kidneys.
Remember that the vast majority of amniotic fluid
is actually the urine of the baby,
and at the same time,
the baby consumes some of that amniotic fluid
by swallowing it,
and when the amniotic fluid is swallowed,
it then gets digested and goes through the GI tract,
and so you can imagine that if the baby
can't swallow amniotic fluid,
they won't be able to remove
some of that fluid physiologically,
and hence there's going to be excess fluid,
and that's called polyhydramnios,
excess amniotic fluid,
so that's the second clinical feature.
The third clinical feature will be that
as the baby breathes,
air will come down into the distal esophagus
and eventually go into the stomach,
and so you'll get abdominal distension,
and then finally,
some of the contents from the stomach
will aspirate back through the distal esophagus
into the trachea,
which will then give you aspiration.
So there are four clinical features
in this most common variant,
and I've written this all very clearly in your text,
so you should be able to follow it there.
Here's an image of a TE fistula.
It's a beautiful gross picture.
You can clearly see that this is the proximal esophagus,
which is atretic.
This is the distal esophagus here,
and it's plugging into the trachea,
and so this is, again,
the most common variant of a TE fistula.
The esophageal web refers to a mucosal protrusion
that results in obstruction or a partial obstruction
with dysphagia for poorly chewed food.
Let me just draw this out again just to remind you.
Let's say that that's the lumen of the esophagus there.
Well, remember that the wall of the esophagus
would contain a mucosa,
and behind that mucosa would be a submucosa,
and then behind the submucosa
would be the muscularis propria,
and then behind the muscularis propria,
you have a cirrhosa.
So these are the four key layers of the GI tract,
and in this particular case,
in an esophageal web,
you get a protrusion of the mucosa,
which then results in a partial obstruction,
which is called a web.
Now, of course, when the patient eats,
especially if they have not chewed their food very well,
so if you have poorly chewed food,
that can present with a little bit of dysphagia
because it gets trapped in this web.
So again, an esophageal web
is a thin protrusion of the mucosa only.
It occurs usually in the upper esophagus,
and it presents with dysphagia for poorly chewed food.
There is an increased risk,
as I've stated here in your text,
for squamous cell carcinoma of the esophagus,
but I'm gonna make this very clear
at the end of the lecture.
So let's skip this point for now,
but just bury it away in the back of your mind
that in an esophageal web,
you get an increased risk for squamous cell carcinoma.
The most important manifestation,
at least for the purposes of board examinations,
of an esophageal web
is something called Plummer-Vincent syndrome.
Recall from our discussions in red blood cell pathology
where we discussed this once before
that in Plummer-Vincent syndrome,
the patients have severe iron deficiency anemia,
an esophageal web, and a beefy red tongue.
Now, that beefy red tongue is basically due to the fact
that they get atrophy of the mucosa,
so they get a little bit of atrophic glossitis,
and the red color is actually
because the blood vessels are exposed.
The next disorder is called a Zenker diverticulum,
and this is an outpouching of the pharyngeal mucosa
through an acquired defect,
acquired defect in the muscular wall.
Basically, what happens is you have abnormal pressure
in the pharynx when you're swallowing,
usually due to some sort of impairment
or disordered swallowing,
and so when this abnormal pressure
develops in the back of the pharynx,
then you get a protrusion of the mucosa
through the muscular wall.
So you can imagine it as such.
If this is the mucosa here,
this layer is the mucosa,
remember that behind it is going to be this muscular wall.
Now, if there's disordered swallowing,
you're going to generate some high pressure
in this particular region,
and then that's going to result in a protrusion
of the mucosa through or backward
through the acquired defect in the muscular wall.
This usually occurs just above the upper esophageal sphincter
at the junction of the esophagus and the pharynx,
and this is the classic location.
Now, patients can be asymptomatic.
Perhaps the most common symptom that they can present with
is that they feel like there's something
in the back of their throat,
but they can also have dysphagia.
They can have obstruction,
and they can have halitosis.
Halitosis refers to bad breath,
and the idea here is that as the food gets trapped
in that diverticulum, it can rot,
and when it rots,
then the smell of the rotting food
will actually come through the mouth,
giving the patient bad breath.
Important to note that when we talk about
this Zenker diverticulum,
this is also known as a false diverticulum.
False diverticulum means that you've only protruded
one part of the wall through the entire wall.
So that's also called a false diverticulum,
and most of the diverticulums in the GI tract
are actually false diverticulums
where part of the wall goes through
another part of the wall.
Mallory-Weiss syndrome is when you get
a longitudinal laceration of the esophageal mucosa
at the GE junction,
and the idea is as follows.
If this is the esophagus,
and you've got the stomach coming off the esophagus,
of course, here is the GE junction.
Now, basically, in this particular disorder,
patients have severe vomiting.
As the vomit goes up,
it also begins to create a linear laceration
of the mucosa at the GE junction.
So that's called Mallory-Weiss syndrome.
Now, of course, because this is all driven by vomiting,
the causes are going to be those
that are associated with severe vomiting.
And so the two causes or the two circumstances
in which we usually see this
are, number one, alcoholics or alcoholism
because of the severe vomiting,
and then bulimics who force themselves to vomit
in order to try to decrease or maintain their weight.
And so that's what would then result
in this linear longitudinal laceration
of the mucosa at the GE junction.
The way this is going to present
is that this laceration is going to bleed,
and so the patients are going to have hematemesis,
which is blood and the vomit.
However, it will also be painful,
and that's particularly important
is that these patients have,
as I've stated here in the text,
painful hematemesis.
Now, there's a risk of something called Borhav syndrome,
and Borhav syndrome is when you get rupture
of the esophagus,
so you can imagine that you can actually
bore through the entire wall of the esophagus
and get rupture.
When you rupture the esophagus,
you get air in the mediastinum.
The air in the mediastinum can then actually
track up through the fascial planes
and eventually get into the subcutaneous tissue,
especially in the region of the neck.
Now, that will then result in something
called subcutaneous emphysema,
where you actually have air bubbles within the,
you can actually push on the air bubbles
within the, or beneath the skin,
and as you push on those air bubbles beneath the skin,
you can actually hear a crackling noise,
almost like Rice Krispies,
and so when you press on that,
you get that crackling noise,
and that is a classic sign of subcutaneous emphysema,
which again, that would be a hint
that you've got some sort of a process
leading to air in the mediastinum,
and in this particular case,
we would think about Borhoff syndrome,
so that's a very high-yield discussion to be aware of.
Esophageal varices are when you get
a dilated submucosal vein in the lower esophagus,
and this is going to arise secondary
to portal hypertension.
Let's remind ourselves of a little bit of anatomy.
Remember that there are two ways
by which the veins of the esophagus drain.
Most of the esophageal blood actually drains
via the azagous vein into the superior vena cava,
but however, there is some of the blood
that drains from the left gastric vein
into the portal vein,
so that some of the blood from the esophagus
does drain into the portal circuit.
Now, if there's portal hypertension,
then we're going to have a backup of blood
into the left gastric vein,
which will also result in a backup of blood
into these veins in the esophagus
that were draining via this pathway,
and so that would result in a dilation of those veins,
and so that's, again, called esophageal varices,
dilated submucosal veins in the lower esophagus,
of course, related to portal hypertension.
Now, these are asymptomatic,
so it's not too problematic.
However, you've got to be very well aware
of the complication, which is that these can rupture,
and if they rupture, the patient's going to present
with hematemesis or the vomiting of blood.
However, it will be painless.
That's very important because, remember,
when we talked about Mallory-Weiss syndrome,
we said that the patients have painful hematemesis,
whereas in esophageal varices,
it's painless hematemesis.
Now, this is very important to be aware of
because it's the most common cause of death in cirrhosis,
so patients who are cirrhotic
obviously have portal hypertension,
and the most common cause of death in those patients
is rupture of an esophageal varice.
And, of course, the second problem that these patients have
is that they have a coagulopathy,
so because their liver is not functioning
and they're not producing their coag factors.
And so this can also complicate further
the fact that you now have got a bleed
without the ability to seal it.
So most common cause of death in cirrhosis.
Achalasia.
A means without, and chalasia means relaxation.
And so one of the key issues in this particular disorder
is that you lose the ability to relax
the lower esophageal sphincter.
In addition, there's disordered esophageal motility
so that you lose motility as well.
So these are the two key problems in achalasia.
Number one, an inability to relax
the lower esophageal sphincter.
And number two, disordered esophageal motility.
So basically, the idea would be as follows,
that if this is the esophagus,
and of course the stomach is coming off the esophagus,
you're well aware of the fact
that in order to move food down this esophagus,
both fluids and solids, fluid and solids
both require peristalsis of this wall.
So that if you lose peristalsis of this wall,
then the patients are going to have dysphagia
for both solids and liquids.
And that's one of the key clinical features
in this particular disorder,
is that the patients have dysphagia
for solids and liquids
because they have an inability,
or they have a loss of the esophageal motility.
The other problem in this particular disorder
is that they've got an inability
to relax that lower esophageal sphincter.
Now, if they can't relax that lower esophageal sphincter,
then what's going to happen
is that food is going to begin to pile up
as it comes in,
and you're going to get massive dilatation
of the esophageal wall.
You can do barium in these patients,
and this massive dilatation will fill up
until you come to the point
where there is this tightening
of the lower esophageal sphincter.
I shouldn't say tightening.
It's actually an inability to relax.
So there is this inability to relax
the lower esophageal sphincter.
The lower esophageal hair looks like a bird beak,
and so they call that the bird beak sign
on barium swallow.
Now, it's important to note
what's causing this disorder.
The cause of this disorder
is the fact that the patients have damage
to the ganglion cells in the myenteric plexus.
Now, let's go back and remind ourselves
of a little bit of normal histology,
and remember that when we talk
about the lumen of the esophagus,
remember that the wall of the esophagus
contains a mucosa,
and then behind that mucosa,
there's a submucosa,
and then behind that submucosa,
there's a muscularis propria,
and then behind that,
there is a serosa.
Now, the muscularis propria
is actually made up of two layers.
There's an inner circular layer,
and there's an outer longitudinal layer,
and in between those two layers
run something called the myenteric plexus.
The myenteric plexus
is a collection of ganglion cells,
and that collection of ganglion cells
is essential for regulating
both bowel motility
and for relaxing
the lower esophageal sphincter.
So if you destroy these ganglion cells,
you're going to lose both
bowel motility
in the region of the esophagus
because that's where it's occurring,
and the inability to relax
that lower esophageal sphincter.
Now, we should then ask the question,
what causes damage
to these ganglion cells?
Well, as I've stated here in your text,
the damage to the ganglion cells
can be idiopathic
or secondary to a known insult,
and one of the classic associations
is Chagas disease
where you can get damage
of the ganglion cells
via this infective process.
Now, here's the classic picture
of the barium swallow,
and what I'm trying to highlight
for you here
is the bird beak sign.
It's a very pretty picture,
the bird beak sign.
This is the dilated wall
of the esophagus,
and this is where
the lower esophageal sphincter
is not relaxing.
And so, again,
this would produce
what we classically call
as a bird beak sign.
Now, the clinical features
of this disorder
are all going to be based
on what I've already explained.
So, there'll be a dysphagia
for both solids and liquids.
And again, you need motility
to move both solids and liquids.
They're going to have putrid breath,
and that's because the solids
are going to accumulate
in the esophagus,
and of course,
that fluid is just going to rot,
and the rotting fluid
will then create very bad breath.
An additional finding
will be that there will be
a high lower esophageal sphincter pressure.
Now, the idea here, again,
is that you've got this dilated wall,
and then you've got tightness
of the lower esophageal sphincter,
so that results in a high pressure
when you do esophageal pressure studies.
And this is a very high-yield association,
and it comes up often on examination,
so you need to know
that the pressure and the LES will be high.
And of course, I think that makes sense
if you understand the disease.
The bird beak sign
I've already talked about,
it's also important to note
that there's an increased risk
for esophageal squamous cell carcinoma,
but again, I'm going to touch on that
when we talk about cancer,
and I'll make that principle
very easy for you.
The next disorder is called GERD,
and GERD refers to gastroesophageal reflux disease.
Now, the idea here is as follows,
that what's going to happen
is that you've got the esophagus,
and then you've got the stomach,
and of course, the stomach is coming off.
This is the lower esophageal sphincter,
and the lower esophageal sphincter
in this particular disorder
is not as tight as it should be,
so there's a decrease in the tone
of the lower esophageal sphincter.
What then happens is that allows for acid
and gastric contents to shoot up
into the esophagus.
When that acid and gastric contents
shoot up into the esophagus,
that then is going to change the stress
on the cells of the lower esophagus
because now they're seeing acid instead of food,
and when they see that acid,
they then undergo a metaplasia
to better deal with the stress.
Now, so initially, remember that the cells
that are lining the esophagus
are non-keratinizing squamous epithelium.
That's the normal lining of the esophagus,
non-keratinizing squamous epithelium,
but what's going to happen
in response to this change in stress
is that you're going to get a change
in the cell type.
The change in the cell type
then becomes non-ciliated columnar cells
with goblet cells,
and that is then, of course, a metaplasia.
Now, let's go back and just review
what we have here in your text.
So, of course, we've already talked about the fact
that you get reflux of acid from the stomach
due to reduced lower esophageal tone.
The risk factors are interesting.
Alcohol, tobacco, obesity, a fat-rich diet, caffeine.
All of these are risk factors.
One that we should particularly emphasize
is something called a hiatal hernia.
So let's take a minute to just explain
what the hiatal hernia is.
Now, basically, again,
you should remember your normal anatomy,
and that is that the esophagus
is the plugging into the stomach, correct?
And, of course, we know that running here
and running here is the diaphragm,
and the diaphragm plays a particularly important role
in helping to maintain
that lower esophageal sphincter, by the way.
Now, what can happen is that
you can get a diaphragmatic hernia
in which the stomach can actually herniate
up into the thorax.
The most common type of diaphragmatic hernia
is actually called a sliding hiatal hernia,
and what happens in this particular case
is that the stomach here
herniates upward into the esophagus,
and that's the most common type again.
It's called a sliding hiatal hernia.
Now, this results in a couple things.
Number one, you've now got
a little bit of part of the stomach,
which really here would be the cardia of the stomach.
So the cardia of the stomach
is up into the esophagus,
and that's going to allow for reflux,
because, again, you really don't have
any sphincter now.
You've just kind of got the stomach
pressing up against the esophagus here,
and so that's going to allow for reflux,
which would then increase the risk
for gastroesophageal reflux disease,
and that's the context in which
we're having this discussion.
Another important thing,
and that's high yield for examinations as well,
is that you're still going to have
the little bit of tone here
in the lower esophageal sphincter.
The lower esophageal sphincter
is normal when you have this hernia,
and so this produces something called
the hourglass appearance of the stomach
with sort of a compression down the middle here,
and so that's an important thing
to be familiar with as well.
Remember that there is another possibility
when you talk about diaphragmatic hernias,
and that is that you could actually develop this,
where you've got the esophagus
and then the stomach coming off,
and then you've got the diaphragm here.
You could actually develop a hernia
such that the stomach actually herniates
up next to the esophagus.
That's called a paraesophageal hernia.
All right, paraesophageal,
because you're herniating a portion of the stomach
up next to the esophagus,
and what's important about this paraesophageal hernia
is that it is, number one, much less common
than the sliding hiatal hernia
that I just described,
and number two, the classic association here
is that you have bowel sounds in the lung fields,
so in the lower lung field,
which of course here would be the lung,
you would actually have bowel sounds
in the lower lung field,
and another important consequence
of having this type of hernia
is that this hernia as it's present congenitally
will result in less space for the lung to develop,
and so these patients can also have lung hypoplasia.
Now I'm making a little bit of a diversion here.
In this particular paraesophageal hernia,
you wouldn't necessarily have GERD,
but I just want to talk about this
for completeness sake
because it does show up on examinations.
Anyway, let's go back to GERD
and just quickly review.
So what are we saying here?
We say that there's reflux of acid
from the stomach due to reduced lower esophageal tone.
I've told you about the risk factors,
and we talked about the hiatal hernia
in which the cardia of the stomach
sort of balloons up into the esophagus,
as I've already explained.
Now the clinical features are all based on the fact
that you're shooting acid into the esophagus.
So the patients get heartburn,
which mimics cardiac chest pain,
and so anytime when a patient comes in
with quote-unquote cardiac chest pain,
you do want to think about heartburn
in the back of your mind
as a possibility for that chest pain.
They also present with asthma and cough.
Now what's interesting about this asthma
is that it is adult-onset asthma.
This isn't asthma that the patient has as a child,
but instead what happens is
they get new-onset asthma as an adult.
And so when you have adult-onset asthma,
you really want to think about
gastroesophageal reflux disease,
and the idea here,
if this is the stomach and the esophagus coming up,
as you get shooting of acid up into the esophagus,
you can irritate the airway as well,
and that can result in asthma and cough.
The acid can also reach the level of the teeth,
which would then cause damage
to the enamel of the teeth.
So that's a clinical feature.
Now some of the consequences
of having all this acid shooting up
into the lower esophagus
is that number one,
you can get ulceration with stricture.
Again, the idea being
that if you've got the esophagus here
and then the stomach coming off
and you're shooting up acid,
you can damage the mucosa so that it ulcerates,
and then when you ulcerate the mucosa,
you've done,
remember that an ulceration
is a complete knockout of the mucosa,
so that if you've got mucosa and submucosa,
when you get an ulceration,
you actually are taking a divot out of the mucosa
along with a little piece of submucosa.
If you knock out the mucosa,
you're knocking out the stem cells,
and the way by which ulcers
are going to heal then is fibrosis.
So you can actually get fibrosis
of this lower region here,
and that can result in a stricture,
and a stricture, again,
is going to result in a loss of the lumen
or at least a narrowing of the lumen
of the lower esophagus.
So that's one complication,
and that is that you can get ulceration with stricture.
A second complication
and a very high-yield complication, again,
is that when you have all of this acid shooting up,
you're going to get the metaplasia
that I've already described,
and that's called Barrett's esophagus.
This is a very high-yield point to be aware of.
Here's a picture of Barrett's esophagus.
I place it here because it's a very common picture
to show up on exams.
Here is the non-keratinizing squamous epithelium
that normally lines the esophagus,
and we've got acid shooting up
and then hitting this particular portion
of the lower esophagus.
This entire slide should represent a normal esophagus,
and you can see
that the non-keratinizing squamous epithelium
has ended abruptly,
and all of a sudden,
we now have these columnar cells.
And let me remind you
that when you think about the metaplasia here,
you get a metaplasia to a non-ciliated columnar epithelium
with goblet cells.
You've got to know that entire phrase,
non-ciliated columnar epithelium with goblet cells.
That's very important.
And so here is this non-ciliated columnar epithelium
with these interspersed goblet cells.
Now, of course,
this is a response of the stem cells
to the acidic stress,
and we've talked about this in detail
in our metaplasia discussions.
Because it's a metaplasia,
it can progress to dysplasia,
and that dysplasia could progress to adenocarcinoma.
So that takes us into a discussion
of esophageal carcinoma.
But let's remind ourselves
that esophageal carcinoma
can be divided into two types,
adenocarcinoma or squamous cell carcinoma.
So in the case of adenocarcinoma,
the most important things to know
are that it's going to be
a malignant proliferation of glands.
Now, you don't normally have glands
within the esophagus,
and so the way by which it's going to occur
is that you're going to get metaplasia,
i.e. Barrett's esophagus,
and which will then turn into an adenocarcinoma
via the dysplasia carcinoma sequence.
Now, of course,
the only way to get this, of course,
is going to be the metaplasia.
Therefore, it's going to occur
in the lower one-third,
because that's exactly
where the metaplasia occurs.
Now, what I can tell you about adenocarcinoma
is that it is the most common type
of esophageal carcinoma in the West.
So that's the summary of adenocarcinoma.
Most common type of esophageal carcinoma in the West
arises from Barrett's esophagus,
lower one-third of the esophagus.
So once you understand the basics about adenocarcinoma,
let's quickly review what I say in the book.
I say adenocarcinoma is a malignant proliferation of glands,
most common type of esophageal carcinoma in the West,
Barrett's esophagus, lower one-third.
Now, the second type of esophageal carcinoma
is squamous cell carcinoma.
This is a malignant proliferation of squamous cells,
and it is the most common esophageal cancer worldwide.
It usually arises in the middle
or upper third of the esophagus.
Now, the risk factors are interesting,
and there's a long list of risk factors
that we can go through,
but let me just summarize this for you
in just one word, irritation.
If you irritate the squamous mucosa,
you are going to increase the risk
for development of squamous cell carcinoma.
So let's talk about some of these
and see how they irritate the mucosa.
Of course, alcohol and tobacco are irritants.
We are well aware of the fact
that they irritate epithelium,
and so they will irritate the mucosa
and result in an increased risk
for squamous cell carcinoma.
Very hot tea.
Places in southern China and Iran
where they tend to drink very hot tea,
there's an increased risk of squamous cell carcinoma
in those particular regions.
You find a relatively high incidence
of squamous cell carcinoma
in that part of the world.
Achalasia can also increase the risk.
Now, how is achalasia going to result in irritation?
Well, you're well aware of the fact
that the problem in achalasia is two things.
You have disordered esophageal motility
and an inability to relax
the lower esophageal sphincter
so that the patients get this classic
bird beak appearance of their esophagus.
Now, imagine that basically
the esophagus is full of food, correct?
And remember that the food
is going to start rotting,
and when it rots,
that's going to irritate the mucosa.
So this rotting food in achalasia
is going to increase the risk
for squamous cell carcinoma of the esophagus.
Esophageal webs can also do it.
Of course, the same idea.
An esophageal web is a protrusion of the mucosa,
which then results in a blocking of food,
particularly when it is poorly chewed.
Now, of course, food is going to pile up
along this web,
and when food piles up along the web,
it's going to rot,
and when it rots,
that then is going to irritate the mucosa.
So there's going to be an increased risk
of squamous cell carcinoma.
And the last risk factor is esophageal injury.
Any patient that has had severe esophageal injury,
for example, lie ingestion,
lie is a chemical that can be used to straighten hair,
and so this chemical could be taken,
for example, by a child by accident,
which would then injure the esophagus,
increasing the risk for squamous cell carcinoma.
Now, important about esophageal carcinoma,
whether it be squamous
or whether it be adenocarcinoma,
it presents very late in the course.
The patients get progressive dysphagia.
What does progressive dysphagia mean?
Progressive dysphagia means
that the dysphagia starts as dysphagia for solids,
and eventually progresses to dysphagia
for both solids and liquids.
So here's a picture of the esophagus,
and you can imagine
that you're growing this tumor in the esophagus.
So initially,
the solids are going to have trouble
passing that tumor,
but eventually,
the tumor is going to become larger,
and as it expands,
that's going to then result in dysphagia
for both solids and liquids.
The patients will present with weight loss,
which is a classic finding in cancer.
There will be pain,
and there could be hematemesis.
Of course,
as the cancer grows,
it's going to expand and stretch the mucosa,
which would result in bleeding
and blood in the vomit or hematemesis.
Now,
in the case of squamous cell carcinoma,
we should additionally recognize
that these patients can present
with hoarse voice and cough,
and the reason they can present with hoarse voice
is because the tumor is up
in the upper part of the esophagus,
and that can result in invasion
through the wall
into the recurrent laryngeal nerve,
and you can also get invasion
through the wall into the trachea,
which would then present with cough.
When patients have esophageal carcinoma,
the cancer will,
as it grows
and eventually picks up additional mutations,
can eventually metastasize,
and it's important to note
there are different regions
of lymph node spread
based on which part of the esophagus we're in.
So this gets back
to a little bit of anatomy,
and so examiners like to go after it
because it's an anatomy tie-in.
If the cancer arises in the upper one-third,
it tends to spread to the cervical nodes.
In the middle one-third,
you'd expect it to spread
to the mediastinal or tracheobronchial nodes,
and if it's in the lower one-third,
you'd expect it to spread
to the celiac or the gastric nodes.
And that's important to note again
because it's an anatomy tie-in.
So that concludes our discussion on esophagus,
and our next section will be on the stomach.